[Music]
millions of americans come down with
bladder infectious urinary tract
infections every year including more
than a million children
most cases stay in the bladder but when
the bacteria creep up into the kidneys
or get into the bloodstream things can
get serious
thankfully we have antibiotics
there's now a pandemic of a new
multi-drug resistant strain of e coli
discovered just in 2008 and now the
so-called st-131 strain went from
unknown to a leading cause of bladder
infections the world over resistant to
even some of our second and third line
antibiotics
and
it's been found in chicken retail
chicken breasts sampled from across the
country documenting a persisting
reservoir of extensively antimicrobial
resistant expect bacteria the extra
intestinal pathogenic e coli including
the st-131 strain in retail chicken
products in the united states suggesting
a potential public health threat
see
urinary tract infections may be food
borne
by which they mean predominantly poultry
chicken and turkey so maybe we shouldn't
be feeding antibiotics to these animals
by the ton
in poultry production
but wait
food-borne bladder infections
what are you doing with that drumstick
no eating contaminated chicken can lead
to the colonization of the rectum with
these bacteria that can then even months
later crawl up into the bladder to cause
an infection the problem of increasing
antimicrobial resistance is so dire that
some experts are predicting that the era
of antibiotics may be coming to an end
ushering in a post antibiotic era in
which common infections and minor
injuries can once again kill
more than eighty percent of e coli
isolated from beef pork and poultry
exhibited resistance
to at least one antibiotics and more
than half from poultry were resistant to
five different drugs
one of the ways this happens is that
viruses called bacteriophages can
transfer antibiotic resistant genes
between bacteria about a quarter of
these viruses isolated from chicken meat
were found able to transduce antibiotic
drug resistance into e coli and one of
the big problems with this is that
disinfectants used to kill bacteria are
in many cases not able to eliminate
these viruses
some of these viruses are even resistant
to bleach at the kinds of concentrations
used in the food industry and likewise
alcohol which is what you find in many
hand sanitizers also unable to harm most
of them
the irony
is that the industry has tried to
intentionally feed these viruses to
chickens
why would they do that it can boost egg
production and hens and increase body
weight gain in broiler chickens to get
them to slaughter weight faster
the only thing that seems to dissuade
the industry
is if anything affects the taste of the
meat that's why the industry had to stop
spraying chickens with benzene to try to
kill off all the parasites the meat
ended up with a distasteful flavor
described as strong acidic musty
medicinal biting objectionable and
tasty
but
what if you buy organic chicken
for another type of bacteria
endorococcus antibiotic resistant bugs
were found in both conventional and
organically raised chicken but were less
common in organic only about one in
three contaminated with drug-resistant
bugs compared to nearly one in two but
in a study of hundreds of prepackaged
retail chicken breasts tested from 99
grocery stores being labeled organic or
antibiotic free did not seem to impact
the contamination levels of antibiotic
resistant e coli from fresh retail
chicken though purchasing meat from
natural food stores appeared to be safer
regardless of how it was labeled
kosher chicken appeared to be the worst
nearly twice the level of antibiotic
resistant e coli contamination compared
to conventional which goes against the
whole concept of kosher no difference in
drug resistance between the e coli swab
from conventional chicken versus organic
and raised without antibiotics chicken
but either way
kosher was worse
but how could organic and raised without
antibiotics chicken not be better
well
it could be cross-contamination at the
slaughter plant so
bugs just jump from one to the other
or it could be the organic chicken
loophole
usta organic standards prohibits the use
of antibiotics and poultry starting
on day two of the animal's life
this is an important loophole since even
antibiotics considered critical for
human health
are routinely injected into one day old
chicks and eggs
which has been directly associated with
antibiotic resistant foodborne
infections
and there was no difference in the
presence of expec bacteria between
organic and conventional the bacteria
implicated in urinary tract infections
these findings suggest that retail
chicken products in the united states
even if they're labeled organic pose a
potential health threat to consumers
because they're contaminated with
extensively antibiotic resistant e coli
and even if we were able to get the
poultry industry to stop using
antibiotics the contamination of chicken
meat with expect bacteria could still
remain a threat
[Music]
foreign